{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Statements: In a one day cricket match, the total runs made by a team were 200. Out of these 160 runs were made by spinners.\nConclusions:\n\n80% of the team consists of spinners.\nThe opening batsmen were spinners.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "According to the statement, 80% of the total runs were made by spinners. So, I does not follow. Nothing about the opening batsmen is mentioned in the statement. So, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The old order changed yielding place to new.\nConclusions:\n\nChange is the law of nature.\nDiscard old ideas because they are old.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, I directly follows from the given statement. Also, it is mentioned that old ideas are replaced by new ones, as thinking changes with the progressing time. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Government has spoiled many top ranking financial institutions by appointing bureaucrats as Directors of these institutions.\nConclusions:\n\nGovernment should appoint Directors of the financial institutes taking into consideration the expertise of the person in the area of finance.\nThe Director of the financial institute should have expertise commensurate with the financial work carried out by the institute.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "According to the statement, Government has spoiled financial institutions by appointing bureaucrats as Directors. This means that only those persons should be appointed as Directors who are experts in finance and are acquainted with the financial work of the institute. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Population increase coupled with depleting resources is going to be the scenario of many developing countries in days to come.\nConclusions:\n\nThe population of developing countries will not continue to increase in future.\nIt will be very difficult for the governments of developing countries to provide its people decent quality of life.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The fact given in I is quite contrary to the given statement. So, I does not follow. II mentions the direct implications of the state discussed in the statement. Thus, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Prime age school-going children in urban India have now become avid as well as more regular viewers of television, even in households without a TV. As a result there has been an alarming decline in the extent of readership of newspapers.\nConclusions:\n\nMethod of increasing the readership of newspapers should be devised. \nA team of experts should be sent to other countries to study the impact of TV. on the readership of newspapers.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement concentrates on the increasing viewership of TV. and does not stress either on increasing the readership of newspapers or making studies regarding the same. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: In Japan, the incidence of stomach cancer is very high, while that of bowel cancer is very low. But Japanese immigrate to Hawaii, this is reversed - the rate of bowel cancer increases but the rate of stomach cancer is reduced in the next generation. All this is related to nutrition - the diets of Japanese in Hawaii are different than those in Japan.\nConclusions:\n\nThe same diet as in Hawaii should be propagated in Japan also.\nBowel cancer is less severe than stomach cancer.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement neither propagates the diet of any of the countries nor compares the two types of cancer. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The Government run company had asked its employees to declare their income and assets but it has been strongly resisted by employees union and no employee is going to declare his income.\nConclusions:\n\nThe employees of this company do not seem to have any additional undisclosed income besides their salary.\nThe employees union wants all senior officers to declare their income first.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Nothing about the details of the employees' income or the cause of their refusal to declare their income and assets, can be deduced from the given statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Monitoring has become an integral part in the planning of social development programmes. It is recommended that Management Information System be developed for all programmes. This is likely to give a feedback on the performance of the functionaries and the efficacy with which services are being delivered.\nConclusions:\n\nAll the social development programmes should be evaluated.\nThere is a need to monitor the performance of workers.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "According to the statement, monitoring and evaluation of social development programmes - their function, performance and efficiency - is absolutely essential. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The T.V. programmes, telecast specially for women are packed with a variety of recipes and household hints. A major portion of magazines for women also contains the items mentioned above.\nConclusions:\n\nWomen are not interested in other things.\nAn average woman's primary interest lies in home and specially in the kitchen.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, nothing about 'other things' is mentioned in the statement. So, I does not follow, Also, since it is mentioned that programmes and magazines for women are stuffed with kitchen recipes and other household hints, it means that women have special interest in these areas. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The distance of 900 km by road between Bombay and Jafra will be reduced to 280 km by sea. This will lead to a saving of Rs. 7.92 crores per annum on fuel. \nConclusions:\n\nTransportation by sea is cheaper than that by road.\nFuel must be saved to the greatest extent", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "According to the statement, sea transport is cheaper than road transport in the case of route from Bombay to Jafra, not in all the cases. So, conclusion I does not follow. The statement stresses on the saving of fuel. So, conclusion II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The manager humiliated Sachin in the presence of his colleagues.\nConclusions:\n\nThe manager did not like Sachin.\nSachin was not popular with his colleagues.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The manager might have humiliated Sachin not because of his dislike but on account of certain negligence or mistake on his part. So, I does not follow. Also, nothing about Sachin's rapport with his colleagues can be deduced from the statement. So, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Women's organisations in India have welcomed the amendment of the Industrial Employment Rules 1946 to curb sexual harassment at the work place.\nConclusions:\n\nSexual harassment of women at work place is more prevalent in India as compared to other developed countries.\nMany organisations in India will stop recruiting women to avoid such problems.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The fact that a certain rule has been more welcomed in a certain country does not imply that the problem is more prevalent there. So, I does not follow. Also, the amendment seeks to discourage only sexual harassment of women and shall in no way discourage employment of women. So, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Nation X faced growing international opposition for its decision to explode eight nuclear weapons at its test site.\nConclusions:\n\nThe citizens of the nation favoured the decision.\nSome powerful countries do not want other nations to become as powerful as they are.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Neither the citizens response to the decision nor the reason for opposition by other nations can be deduced from the statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: In a highly centralised power structure, in which even senior cabinet ministers are prepared to reduce themselves to pathetic countries or yesmen airing views that are primarily intended to anticipate or reflect the Prime Minister's own performances, there can be no place for any consensus that is quite different from real or contrived unanimity of opinion, expressed through a well orchestrated endorsement of the leader's actions.\nConclusions:\n\nThe Ministers play safe by not giving anti-government views.\nThe Prime Minister does not encourage his colleagues to render their own views.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the statement, even senior cabinet ministers are always ready to conform to the Prime Minister's views. So, I follows. However, II contradicts the given statement and so does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: National Aluminium Company has moved India from a position of shortage to self-sufficiency in the metal.\nConclusions:\n\nPreviously, India had to import aluminium.\nWith this speed, it can soon become a foreign exchange earner.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "According to the statement, National Aluminium Company has moved India from a position of shortage in the past to self-sufficiency in the present. This means that previously, India had to import aluminium. So, I follows. Also, it can be deduced that if production increases at the same rate, India can export it in future. So, II also follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Jade plant has thick leaves and it requires little water.\nConclusions:\n\nAll plants with thick leaves require little water.\nJade plants may be grown in places where water is not in abundance.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement talks of jade plants only and not 'all plants with thick leaves'. So, I does not follow. Also, since jade plants require little water, so they can be grown in places where water is not in abundance. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Use \"Kraft\" colours. They add colour to our life. - An advertisement.\nConclusions:\n\nCatchy slogans do not attract people.\nPeople like dark colours.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The slogan given in the statement is definitely a catchy one which indicates that catchy slogans do attract people. So, I does not follow. Nothing about people's preference for colours can be deduced from the statement. Thus, II also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: All those political prisoners were released on bail who had gone to jail for reasons other than political dharnas. Bail was not granted to persons involved in murders.\nConclusions:\n\nNo political - prisoner had committed murder.\nSome politicians were not arrested.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the statement, the political prisoners can be divided into two groups - those who were released and those who were put in jail for political dharnas. However, no person involved in murder was released. This means that no political prisoner had committed murder. So, I follows. Clearly, II is not directly related to the statement and does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Modern man influences his destiny by the choice he makes unlike in the past.\nConclusions:\n\nEarlier there were fewer options available to man.\nThere was no desire in the past to influence the destiny.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, I directly follows from the statement while II cannot be deduced from it."}, {"question": "Statements: Water supply in wards A and B of the city will be affected by about 50% on Friday because repairing work of the main lines is to be carried out.\nConclusions:\n\nThe residents in these wards should economise on water on Friday.\nThe residents in these wards should store some water on the previous day.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the information has been given beforehand so that the residents can collect water on the previous day and use less water on Friday. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: People who speak too much against dowry are those who had taken it themselves.\nConclusions:\n\nIt is easier said than done.\nPeople have double standards.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement clearly implies that it is easier to say than to do something and what people say is different from what they do. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The national norm is 100 beds per thousand populations but in this state, 150 beds per thousand are available in the hospitals.\nConclusions:\n\nOur national norm is appropriate.\nThe state's health system is taking adequate care in this regard.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Whether the national norm is appropriate or not cannot be said. So, I does not follow. However, more number of beds per thousand population are available in the state. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Our securities investments carry market risk. Consult your investment advisor or agent before investing.\nConclusions:\n\nOne should not invest in securities.\nThe investment advisor calculates the market risk with certainty.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Investment in securities involves risk. This does not mean that one should not invest in securities. So, I does not follow. Since the statement advises one to consult investment advisor before investing, so II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Money plays a vital role in politics.\nConclusions:\n\nThe poor can never become politicians.\nAll the rich men take part in politics.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Neither the poor nor the rich, but only the role of money in politics is being talked about in the statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Vegetable prices are soaring in the market.\nConclusions:\n\nVegetables are becoming a rare commodity.\nPeople cannot eat vegetables.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The availability of vegetables is not mentioned in the given statement. So, I does not follow Also, II is not directly related to the statement and so it also does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The serious accident in which a person was run down by a car yesterday had again focused attention on the most unsatisfactory state of roads.\nConclusions:\n\nThe accident that occurred was fatal.\nSeveral accidents have so far taken place because of unsatisfactory state of roads.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Since the accident has caused concern, it must be fatal. So, I follows. The use of the word 'again' in the statement justifies the fact mentioned in II. So, II also follows."}, {"question": "Statements: In a recent survey report, it has been stated that those who undertake physical exercise for at least half an hour a day are less prone to have any heart ailments.\nConclusions:\n\nModerate level of physical exercise is necessary for leading a healthy life.\nAll people who do desk-bound jobs definitely suffer from heart ailments.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The statement mentions that chances of heart ailments are greatly reduced by a regular half-hour exercise. So, I follows. However, it talks of only reducing the probability which does not mean that persons involved in sedentary jobs shall definitely suffer from heart ailments. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: A bird in hand is worth two in the bush.\nConclusions:\n\nWe should be content with what we have.\nWe should not crave for what is not.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Both the given conclusions clearly bring out the central theme of the proverb given in the statement. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: This world is neither good nor evil; each man manufactures a world for himself.\nConclusions:\n\nSome people find this world quite good.\nSome people find this world quite bad.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement mentions that the world for a man is as he makes it himself. So, some people might find it good and some quite bad. Thus, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The eligibility for admission to the course is minimum second class Master's degree. However, the candidates who have appeared for the final year examination of Master's degree can also apply.\nConclusions:\n\nAll candidates who have yet to get their Master's degree will be there in the list of selected candidates.\nAll candidates having obtained second class Master's degree will be there in the list of selected candidates.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement mentions that the candidates who have obtained second class Master's degree or have appeared for the final year examination of Master's degree, can apply for admission. This implies that both types of candidates may be selected on certain grounds. Thus, some candidates of each type and not all candidates of any one type, may be selected. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Any student who does not behave properly while in the school brings bad name to himself and also for the school.\nConclusions:\n\nSuch student should be removed from the school.\nStricter discipline does not improve behaviour of the students.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, I cannot be deduced from the statement. Also, nothing about discipline is mentioned in the statement. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: A Corporate General Manager asked four managers to either submit their resignations by the next day or face termination orders from service. Three of them had submitted their resignations by that evening.\nConclusions:\n\nThe next day, the remaining manager would also resign.\nThe General Manager would terminate his services the next day.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It is mentioned in the statement that either the managers should resign by the next day or their services would be terminated. So, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Only good singers are invited in the conference. No one without sweet voice is a good singer.\nConclusions:\n\nAll invited singers in the conference have sweet voice. \nThose singers who do not have sweet voice are not invited in the conference.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement asserts that a good singer always has a sweet voice and only good singers are invited in the conference. This implies that all those invited in the conference have sweet voice and those who do not have sweet voice are not invited. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: To cultivate interest in reading, the school has made it compulsory from June this year for each student to read two books per week and submit a weekly report on the books.\nConclusions:\n\nInterest in reading can be created by force.\nSome students will eventually develop interest in reading.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, the new scheme intends to develop interest in reading by incorporating the habit in their routine. So, only II follows while I does not."}, {"question": "Statements: Applications of applicants who do no fulfil eligibility criteria and/or who do not submit applications before last date will be summarily rejected and will not be called for the written test.\nConclusions:\n\nThose who are called for the written test are those who fulfil eligibility criteria and have submitted their applications before last date.\nWritten test will be held only after scrutiny of applications.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "The statement clearly mentions that fulfilling the eligibility criteria and submitting the application before the stipulated date are both essential to avoid rejection. So, I follows. Also, since it is given that the candidates whose applications are rejected shall not be called for written test, so II also follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Recent trends also indicate that the number of child migrants in large cities is increasing. These children leave their families to join the ranks of urban poor doing odd jobs in markets, workshops, hotels or in service sectors.\nConclusions:\n\nMigration to big cities should be checked. \nThe plight of poor children should be thoroughly studied.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statement mentions the problem of increased migration of children to cities. But the ways to deal with the problem cannot be deduced from it. So, neither I nor II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: No country is absolutely self-dependent these days.\nConclusions:\n\nIt is impossible to grow and produce all that a country needs.\nCountrymen in general have become lazy.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, only I provides a suitable explanation to the given statement. So, only I follows."}, {"question": "Statements: The percentage of the national income shared by the top 10 per cent of households in India is 35.\nConclusions:\n\nWhen an economy grows fast, concentration of wealth in certain pockets of population takes place. \nThe national income is unevenly distributed in India.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Nothing about the growth of economy is mentioned in the statement. So, I does not follow. Also, it is given that 35 per cent of national income is shared by 10 per cent of households. This indicates unequal distribution. So, II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Players who break various records in a fair way get special prizes. Player X broke the world record but was found to be under the influence of a prohibited drug.\nConclusions:\n\nX will get the special prize.\nX will not get the special prize.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Clearly, X will not get the special prize because although he broke the world record, he was found to use unfair means. So, II follows while I does not."}, {"question": "Statements: Company X has marketed the product. Go ahead; purchase it if price and quality are your considerations.\nConclusions:\n\nThe product must be good in quality.\nThe price of the product must be reasonable.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "It is mentioned in the statement that one who considers price and quality before buying a product should buy the product of company X. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Quality has a price tag. India is allocating lots of funds to education.\nConclusions:\n\nQuality of education in India would improve soon.\nFunding alone can enhance quality of education.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "According to the statement, funding is necessary to improve quality and India is allocating funds to education. This means that quality of education will improve in India. So, I follows. But funding alone is sufficient to enhance quality, is not true. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Although we have rating agencies like Crisil, ICRA, there is demand to have a separate rating agency for IT companies to protect investors.\nConclusions:\n\nAssessment of financial worth of IT companies calls for separate set of skills, insight and competencies. \nNow the investors investing in IT companies will get protection of their investment.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The need for separate rating agency for IT companies clearly indicates that such assessment requires a separate set of skills. So, I follows. However, the statement indicates only the need or demand and neither the future course of action nor its after-effects can be judged. So, II does not follow."}, {"question": "Statements: The standard of education in private schools is much better than Municipal and Zila Parishad-run schools.\nConclusions:\n\nThe Municipal and Zila Pariskad should make serious efforts to improve standard of their schools.\nAll Municipal and Zila Parishad schools should be closed immediately.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clearly, the solution to the problem is not to close down the Municipal and Zila Parishad-run schools but to strive to improve the standard of education of these schools. So, only I follows while II does not."}, {"question": "Statements: All the organised persons find time for rest. Sunita, in spite of her very busy schedule, finds time for rest.\nConclusions:\n\nSunita is an organised person.\nSunita is an industrious person.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Sunita has a very busy schedule. This means that she is industrious. But still she finds time for rest. This means that she is an organised person. So, both I and II follow."}, {"question": "Statements: Domestic demand has been increasing faster than the production of indigenous crude oil.\nConclusions:\n\nCrude oil must be imported.\nDomestic demand should be reduced.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The statement mentions that demand for oil is increasing faster than the production. So, either the demand must be reduced or oil must be imported to cope with the increasing demand. Thus, either I or II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: He stressed the need to stop the present examination system and its replacement by other methods which would measure the real merit of the students.\nConclusions:\n\nExaminations should be abolished.\nThe present examination system does not measure the real merit of the students.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement stresses the need to adopt a new method of examination. So, I does not follow. However, II directly follows from the given statement."}, {"question": "Statements: Fashion is a form of ugliness so intolerable that we have to alter it every six months.\nConclusions:\n\nFashion designers do not understand the public mind very well.\nThe public by and large is highly susceptible to novelty.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The statement asserts that people cannot stand any particular trend for long and seek change quite often. So, only II follows."}, {"question": "Statements: Until our country achieves economic equality, political freedom and democracy would be meaningless.\nConclusions:\n\nPolitical freedom and democracy go hand in hand.\nEconomic equality leads to real political freedom and democracy.", "opta": "Only conclusion I follows", "optb": "Only conclusion II follows", "optc": "Either I or II follows", "optd": "Neither I nor II follows", "opte": "Both I and II follow", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Nothing about the relation between political freedom and democracy is mentioned in the statement. So, I does not follow. But II directly follows from the given statement."}]]}